Gellis, Mortimer Insurance Workers International Union Papers 6401
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mortimer Gellis Insurance Workers International Union Papers
1937-1981
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gellis, Mortimer
Insurance Workers International Union (IWIU)
6401
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, constitutions, news clippings, photographs.
8791363
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 24, 2015
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, May 11, 2015
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arbitration; Insurance worker (Washington, D.C.: 1954); Daily worker (Chicago, Ill.); C.I.O. debit; Insurance worker (Washington, D.C.: 1958); Newsletter of Local 1706, Industrial Insurance Employees Union, CIO; Abramson, Irving; Belser, Jack; Berney, Leon W.; Butler, William ("Bill"); Crima, Anthony ("Tony"); Drury, Patrick J.; Fitzmaurice, David J.; Gellis, Mortimer; Gillen, William A.; Hauens, C. Hauens; Heisel, Charles G.; Helfgott, Simon; Hill, James C.; Kane, W. Edward; Lawrence, R. P.; Lincoln, Leroy A.; McGoldrick, Joe; Merrill, Lewis; Miller, Frank B.; Murdock, William O.; Pollack, Joseph; Provenzano, John J.; Robinson, Rob; Roosevelt, Franklin Deleno; Schneider, Aaron D.; Young, Malcolm C.; Zaruba, Frank H.; Industrial Insurance Employees Union (IIEU), Local 30, United Office and Professional Workers of America (UOPWA), CIO; Industrial Insurance Employees Union (IIEU), Local 1706, CIO; Insurance Agents' International Union (IAIU), AFL; Insurance Agents' International Union (IAIU), AFL-CIO; Insurance Agents' International Union (IAIU), Local 5, AFL-CIO; Insurance Men's Benevolent Association; Insurance Workers International Union (IWIU), AFL-CIO; Insurance Workers International Union (IWIU), Local 5, AFL-CIO; Insurance Workers of America (IWA), CIO; Insurance Workers of America(IWA), AFL-CIO; John Hancock Life Insurance Company; Metropolitan Life Insurance Company; National Labor Relations Board (NLRB); National War Labor Board (NWLB); United Office and Professional Workers of America (UOPWA), CIO, Brooklyn, NY; United Office and Professional Workers of America (UOPWA), CIO, Cleveland, Ohio
8791363
- Union Constitutions, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO Revised, Cleveland, Ohio, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Format: Constitutions and By-Laws.
  - Item 2: United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO Revised, Cleveland, Ohio, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO Revised, Brooklyn, NY, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: Insurance Mens Benevolent Association, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: Insurance Workers of America, CIO, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 6: Insurance Workers of America, CIO, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copy 2.
  - Item 7: Insurance Workers of America, CIO, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 8: Insurance Agents International Union, AFL, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 9: Insurance Agents International Union, AFL-CIO, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 10: Insurance Workers of America, AFL-CIO, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 11: Insurance Workers of America, AFL-CIO, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 12: Insurance Workers of America, AFL-CIO, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 13: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 14: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 15: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 16: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 17: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 18: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 19: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Union By-Laws, 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: By-laws of the Industrial Insurance Employees Union, Local 30, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dated June 19, 1947
  - Item 2: By-laws of the Industrial Insurance Employees Union, Local 30, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: By-laws of the Industrial Insurance Employees Union, Local 30, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dated June 19, 1947 with handwritten edits changing the local union to Local 1706 of the Industrial Insurance Employees Union
  - Item 4: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws Amendments, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dealing with the number of full time officers and the rights of officers to receive a pension from the Union. Amendments to take effect March 1, 1969.
  - Item 5: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws Amendments, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dealing with the number of full time officers and the rights of officers to receive a pension from the Union. Amendments to take effect March 1, 1969. Copy 2.
  - Item 6: By-laws of Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 9: Proposed Additions and Amendments to Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 10: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 11: Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO Proposed By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 12: Proposed By-Laws Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Proposed By-laws of Local 5, Insurance Workers International Union, merging Local 19 and Local 1706 as well as proposed amendments (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Contract between the Insurance Agents International Union, AFL-CIO and the Prudential Insurance Company of America, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Information on Premium Rates, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Insurance form 398. National Service Life Insurance
- Documents dealing with voluntary arbitration between the Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO and the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Including the Memorandum for the Union dated May 9, 1961 and the Award of the Arbitrator dated September 18, 1961
- Metropolitan Life Insurance Company Court and NLRB Cases, 1943-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Ruling of the National War Labor Board Region II, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dated September 15, 1943 in the matter of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company and the Industrial Insurance Agents Union, Local 30, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO
    Format: Text.
  - Item 2: Statement by Leroy A. Lincoln, President of Metropolitan Life Insurance Company to the National War Labor Board, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dated September 18, 1944. Dealing with the decision concerning compensation of agents
  - Item 3: Escrow Agreement, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    September 29, 1944. Between Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, the Escrowees, and Manufacturers' Trust Company, Depositary.
  - Item 4: Ruling of the United States District Court, Southern District of New York, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dated June 12, 1946 in the matter of Paris, Rogers, Mfyrich, Levy, Schechter, and Rosenbaum, Plaintiffs against Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, Berney, North, and Nicholas, Defendants
  - Item 5: Letter from R. P. Lawrence, Second Vice-President, Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    June 14, 1949. Regarding negotiations with UOPWA over the Escrow fund.
    Format: Letter.
  - Item 6: Decision of the National Labor Relations Board, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dated November 10, 1950 in the matter of Metropolitan Life Insurance Company and United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, Case No.2-CA-992
  - Item 7: Documents dealing with a court case heard in the US District Court, Southern District of NY, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Plaintiffs were agents and former agents of Metropolitan Life Insurance Company; defendants were Metropolitan Life Insurance Company and several officers of the company
- Correpondence, 1955-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: To "Bro Ellis", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    July 14, 1955.
  - Item 2: William O. Murdock, Director of Industrial Relations, John Hancock Life Insurance Company, to M. Gellis President, Local 1706, IWIU, AFL-CIO, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    October 19, 1959. Dealing with disputes between the company and the union
  - Item 3: Esther Helfgott, widow of Simon Helfgott, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    May 3, 1959 accompanied by a letter of the same date to the Officers and Executive Board of Local 1706, IWA, AFL-CIO, acknowledging the dedication of room in the union office in memory of her late husband.
  - Item 4: Joe McGoldrick, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    May 26, 1960 on the occasion of a testimonial dinner for Mr. McGoldrick
  - Item 5: Patrick J. Drury, John Hancock Life Insurance Company, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    May 3, 1962 on the occasion of Mr. Drury's retirement
  - Item 6: C. Hauens, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    November 1962 acknowledging assistance given by the union
  - Item 7: 18 Telegrams sent to M. Gellis on the occasion of a testimonial dinner in his honor, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    December 10, 1964.
  - Item 8: Irving Abramson, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    December 15, 1964. Regarding testimonial dinner on December 10, 1964.
  - Item 9: Leon W. Berney, C.L.U. and M. Gellis, President of Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    July 1966.
  - Item 10: W. Edward Kane, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    February 28, 1969. 2 copies.
  - Item 11: Mortimer Gellis and William Gillen, President of the Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    October 15, 1969. Dealing with the rights of retired union members
  - Item 12: Irving Abramson, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    October 31, 1969.
  - Item 13: Mortimer Gellis and William Gillen, President of the Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    November 5, 1969. Dealing with constitutional issues
  - Item 14: David J. Fitzmaurice, Secretary-Treasure, International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    November 18, 1969.
  - Item 15: Irving Abramson, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    December 23, 1969.
  - Item 16: Frank B. Miller, President and CEO, John Hancock Insurance, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    February 10, 1970.
  - Item 17: Irving Abramson, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    April 22, 1971. Regarding Mr. Abramson's retirement.
  - Item 18: Irving Abramson, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    May 10, 1971.
  - Item 19: Joseph Pollack, President of the Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    August 27, 1977.
  - Item 20: Charles G. Heisel, Secretary-Treasurer of the Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    August 29, 1977.
  - Item 21: Frank H. Zaruba, President of Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    November 16, 1977.
  - Item 22: Mortimer Gellis to Rob Robinson, editor of the Insurance Worker magazine (IWIU, AFL-CIO), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    January 1, 1981. Dealing with the history of the union in the 1950's including events leading up to the merger of the two insurance workers unions and a handwritten transcript of remarks by M. Gellis at a union meeting July 14, 1955 dealing with the elect
  - Item 23: William (Bill) Butler, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    February 25, 1981 in response to item #10. It appears that following the letter from M. Gellis to Rob Robinson a subsequent article was published in the Insurance Worker magazine.
  - Item 24: Anthony (Tony) Crima, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    March 18, 1981 responding to a March 10 letter from M. Gellis on the occasion of Mr. Crima's retirement
- Union Circulars, 1949-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Aaron D. Schneider, Greater New York Regional Council, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, to All Local Union Organizers, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    August 8, 1949. Regarding the NY area to protest the trial of 12 Communists.
  - Item 2: Aaron D. Schneider, Greater New York Regional Council, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, to All Local Union Organizers, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    September 12, 1949. Regarding the NY area to protest the trial of 12 Communists.
  - Item 3: Aaron D. Schneider, Greater New York Regional Council, United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO, to All Local Union Organizers, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    October 4, 1949. Regarding the NY area to protest the trial of 12 Communists.
  - Item 4: Letter dated December 8, 1950 from Malcolm C. Young, Second Vice-President of John Hancock Mutual Life Insurance Company to District Agents. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 5: Jack Belser to the membership of Local 1706 endorsing M. Gellis for president of the local., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    November 1952.
  - Item 6: John J. Provenzano regarding the 1969 Union election (Box 1, Folder 9)
    January 31, 1969.
  - Item 7: William A. Gillen regarding amended constitution, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    August 20, 1969.
- Union Publications, 1950-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: The Daily Worker, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Dated May 19, 1950
    Format: News clipping.
  - Item 2: The CIO Debit, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Official Publication of the Industrial Insurance Employees Union, Local 1706, IAWOC, CIO dated December 1950
    Format: Pamphlet.
  - Item 3: Newsletter of Local 1706, Industrial Insurance Employees Union, CIO, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes mention of Local 30 UOPWA as well as the lifting of the "Negro ban"
    Format: Newsletter.
  - Item 4: Publication of the UOPWA (DPOWA), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    from early 1951 reflecting the dispute with the IAWOC, CIO.
  - Item 5: The AFL-CIO Insurance Worker, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    September, 1957.
  - Item 6: The Insurance Worker, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Magazine published by the Insurance Workers of America, AFL-CIO dated March 1959; much of the issue is devoted to the forthcoming merger of the IWA and the Insurance Agents International Union.
  - Item 7: The AFL-CIO Insurance Worker, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    July 1959.
  - Item 8: The AFL-CIO Insurance Worker, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    August, 1979.
- Meeting Minutes, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  January 1, 1955.
- Local 5 IWIU Executive Board Minutes and Other Documents, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 1: Local 5 IWIU Executive Board Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    February 3, 1977.
  - Item 2: Local 5 IWIU Executive Board Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    April 7, 1977.
  - Item 3: Local 5 IWIU Executive Board Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    May 5, 1977.
  - Item 4: IWIU, AFL-CIO Financial Statements, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    December 31, 1978.
  - Item 5: Information sent to union members concerning 1978 negotiations between IWIU, AFL-CIO and Metropolitan Life Insurance Company. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Property at no.39-40 Glenwood Ave., Little Neck, NY., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 1: Plat of 39-40 Glenwood Ave., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Surveyed June 20, 1952.
  - Item 2: Statement of Closing of Title to Premises 39-40 Glenwood Ave., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    June 26, 1952.
- News Clippings, 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 1: New York Times obituary dated June 20, 1965 for Lewis Merrill, a former leader of UOPWA. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 2: Article from the Wall Street Journal, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Dated March 7, 1968 dealing with a Supreme Court decision that insurance salesmen/commission agents are "employees" within the scope of the National Labor Relations Act and as such cleared the way for union organizing attempts.
  - Item 3: A long article from the New York Times Magazine, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Dated November 14, 1971 profiling the career of Leonard Boudin, a well-known attorney who defended left-wing activists and causes.
  - Item 4: Metropolitan Life's Failure as a Swingerr, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    From Business Week, November 21, 1977.
- Membership cards, 1937-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 1: United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO Industrial Insurance Agents Union division, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Format: Union Membership Card.
  - Item 2: United Office and Professional Workers of America, CIO Industrial Insurance Agents Union division, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 3: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 4: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 5: Insurance Workers International Union, AFL-CIO, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Poem (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Handwritten
- ILR Song Sheets, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  January 6, 1965.
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Item 1: A photo of President Franklin D. Roosevelt signing a document; date unknown; among those present is Francis Perkins. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Format: black and white photograph.
  - Item 2: Photograph apparently of the officers and Executive Board of the IWIU, AFL-CIO (Box 1, Folder 18)
    circa mid-1960s. Includes Mortimer Gellis and Edward Kane among others.
  - Item 3: Photograph apparently of the officers and leadership of Local 5, IWIU, AFL-CIO, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Dated January 7, 1965 signed by George A. Rollins. Includes Eugen Lefeure, Mortimer Gellis, Edward Kane, and Mimis Therry among others.
  - Item 4: Photograph of Mortimer Gellis and two others (Box 1, Folder 18)